Guide to the Booker T. Washington correspondence, 1903-1916, 1933 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Booker T. Washington correspondence 1903-1916, 1933 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Washington, Booker T., 1856-1915
.5 Linear Feet 107 Items
American educator, born a slave in Franklin County, Virginia. Founder and president of Tuskegee Institute in Tuskegee, Alabama.
Collection comprises correspondence and related material concerning the Carnegie Hall conference (January 6-8, 1904) and the subsequent formation of the Committee of Twelve for the Advancement of the Negro Race by Booker T. Washington and W.E.B. Du Bois. The letters in the collection document the Committee of Twelve's work, contain commentary on the status of African Americans, and detail Washington's relationships with many of the key African American leaders of his day. The most striking is Washington's correspondence with W.E.B. Du Bois, where the tension and ideological conflict between the two men is clearly demonstrated. Other prominent correspondents include Charles W. Chestnutt, John S. Durham, Thomas Fortune, Marcus Garvey, Archibald Grimké; Francis J. Grimké, James Weldon Johnson, Judson W. Lyons, Fredrick L. McGhee, Whitefield McKinlay, Kelly Miller, Robert R. Moton, Charles W. Russell, Emmett J. Scott, and Alexander Walters. Acquired as part of the John Hope Franklin Research Center for African and African American History and Culture.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Original correspondence is closed to use; copies are available for access.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Booker T. Washington correspondence was received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2002.
Biographical Note
Booker Taliaferro Washington, American educator, civil rights advocate, author, writer, and orator, was born a slave in Franklin County, Virginia, April 5, 1856. Founder and president of Tuskegee Institute in Tuskegee, Alabama (1881), Washington was a spokesman for the post-Reconstruction conservative viewpoint among African Americans who favored self-improvement, industrial education, and acquiescence to segregation, rather than agitation for more extensive civil and political rights. W.E.B. DuBois criticized this stance and called Washington "The Great Accommodator." Among Washington's written works are My life and work (1900), and Up from slavery (1901), The man farthest down (1912), and many articles and speeches. Following a sudden health crisis in New York City, Washington died in Tuskegee, Alabama on November 14, 1915, at the age of 59.
Collection Overview
The collection comprises over 90 pieces of correspondence and related materials concerning the Carnegie Hall Conference (January 6-8, 1904) and the subsequent formation of the Committee of Twelve for the Advancement of the Interest of the Negro Race. The conference was a critical event in the early history of the African American civil rights movement. It was organized by Washington and W.E.B. Du Bois, and it brought together many of the most prominent African American leaders in the United States. The Committee broke up in 1905 due to differences between the leaders.
The letters in the collection provide documentary evidence for the Committee of Twelve's evolution and work, as well as commentary on the status of African Americans. They detail Washington's relationships with many of the key African American leaders of his day. The most striking is Washington's correspondence with W.E.B. Du Bois, where the tension and ideological conflict between the two men is clearly demonstrated. Other prominent correspondents include Charles W. Chestnutt, John S. Durham, Thomas Fortune, Marcus Garvey, Archibald Grimké; Francis J. Grimké, James Weldon Johnson, Judson W. Lyons, Fredrick L. McGhee, Whitefield McKinlay, Kelly Miller, Robert R. Moton, Charles W. Russell, Emmett J. Scott, and Alexander Walters.
Other materials in the collection include copies of the pamphlet Why disfranchisement is bad (July 1904); a photocopy of and a copy of the original article, The estimate of an eminent Virginian of the merit of the book THE WHITE MAN'S BURDEN; and a poem, The Empty Sleeve.
Acquired as part of the John Hope Franklin Research Center for African and African American History and Culture.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Chesnutt, Charles W. (Charles Waddell), 1858-1932
Committee of Twelve for the Advancement of the Interests of the Negro Race
Du Bois, W.E.B. (William Edward Burghardt), 1868-1963
Durham, John S.
Fortune, Timothy Thomas, 1856-1928
Garvey, Marcus, 1887-1940
Grimké, Archibald Henry, 1849-1930
Grimké, Francis J. (Francis James), 1850-1937
Johnson, James Weldon, 1871-1938
Lyons, Judson Whitlocke, 1860-1924
McGhee, Fredrick L., 1861-1912
McKinlay, Whitefield, 1857-1941
Miller, Kelly, 1863-1939.
Moton, Robert Russa, 1867-1940
Russell, Charles Wells, 1856-1927
Scott, Emmett J. (Emmett Jay), 1873-1957
Walters, Alexander, b. 1858
Washington, Booker T., 1856-1915
African Americans -- United States
African American intellectuals -- Correspondence
African American political activists
African Americans -- Civil rights -- History
African Americans -- Politics and government
African Americans -- History -- 1877-1964
Civil rights movements -- United States -- History -- 20th century
United States -- Race relations
United States -- Politics and government -- 1865-1900
John Hope Franklin Research Center for African and African American History and Culture
Contents of Collection
- Correspondence Series, 1903-1933 and undated, (8 folders)
  The bulk of the correspondence relates to the Carnegie Hall Conference (January 6-8, 1904) and the subsequent formation of the Committee of Twelve, as well as issues that arose from these events. The letters in the collection provide documentary evidence for these events, as well as commentaries on the status of African Americans. They detail Washington's relationships with many of the key African-American leaders of his day. Additionally, there are a few letters that are unrelated to B. T. Washington, but are specific to other leading figures from the African diaspora in the Americas.
  Original correspondence is closed to use. Access copies are available in the collection.
  - Whitefield McKinlay to Booker T. Washington, 15 February 1903, Washington, DC, 2 pages (Box 1)
    McKinlay speaks of his meeting with the President during which they did not reach a compromise; he suggests they force a formal vote in the Senate.
  - Judson W. Lyons to Washington, 16 February 1903, Washington, DC, 1 page (Box 1)
    Lyons agrees to attend conference proposed by Washington.
  - Kelly Miller to Washington, 17 February 1903, Washington, DC, 1 page (Box 1)
    Miller agrees to participate in conference treating "the situation which confronts our race"; suggests that each participant pay his own expenses.
  - W. E. B. DuBois to Washington, 20 February 1903, Atlanta, 1 page (Box 1)
    DuBois regrets that Washington has invited Mr. Fortune to attend conference; proposes that Washington write directly to Mr. Morgan.
  - DuBois to Washington, 25 February 1903, Atlanta, 1 page (Box 1)
    DuBois requests a list of conference attendees.
  - DuBois to Washington, 20 March 1903, Atlanta, 1 page (Box 1)
    DuBois requests that conference take place in March rather than April.
  - Fortune to Washington, 31 October 1903, Red Bank, New Jersey, 4 pages (Box 1)
    Fortune encourages Washington to clarify his positions on "industrial and higher education" as well as on "the Southern disfranchising constitutions and our measure of political activity." Fortune also refers to Mr. Scott and a tentative plan for financial support.
  - McKinlay to Washington, 2 November 1903, Washington, DC, 1 page (Box 1)
    McKinlay will try to arrange the conference and agrees that it should be kept secret; McKinlay supports idea of Washington's delivering an address at the conference.
  - DuBois to Washington, 3 November 1903, Atlanta, 1 page (Box 1)
    DuBois approves circular letter and suggests names to be invited.
  - Miller to Washington, 3 November 1903, Washington, DC, 2 pages (Box 1)
    Miller agrees to attend New York conference; Miller requests that Washington be present at sociological conference in Washington as his presence will be vital.
  - Lyons to Washington, 4 November 1903, Washington, DC, 1 page (Box 1)
    Lyons urges them not to make any political mistakes due to upcoming presidential election; agrees to Washington's proposed meeting if it abides by party efforts.
  - Washington to DuBois, 5 November 1903, location unknown, 2 pages (Box 1)
    Washington requests DuBois's opinion as to whether to invite Bishop Turner or Bishop Holsey to New York conference; he suggests they invite a representative from Texas; Washington is making arrangements for their reception in Chicago.
    Published in: Harlan, Louis R. and Raymond W. Smock, eds., The Booker T. Washington Papers. Urbana: U of Illinois Press, 1977. Vol.7, p. 331-332 NB: Their version includes a postscript not in the Rubenstein Library copy.
    Source: TL; W.E.B. DuBois Papers; U of Massachusetts, Amherst
  - Washington to Lyons, 8 November 1903, location unknown, 1 page (Box 1)
    Washington regrets that Lyons views conference as a danger to their party's success; he would like Lyons to represent their political interests at conference and requests that he confirm his presence or absence at said conference.
    Published in: Harlan, Louis R. and Raymond W. Smock, eds., The Booker T. Washington Papers. Urbana: U of Illinois Press, 1977. Vol.7, p. 338
    Source: TLcarbon; BTW Papers; Tuskegee Institute, Alabama
  - Washington to DuBois, 8 November 1903, location unknown, 2 pages (Box 1)
    Washington requests DuBois's opinions on whom else to invite to New York conference; He also warns that since many blacks live in the South, they must invite Southern men who can speak of the Southern experience firsthand.
    Published in: Harlan, Louis R. and Raymond W. Smock, Eds. The Booker T. Washington Papers. Urbana: U of Illinois Press, 1977. Vol. 7, p. 339
    Source: TLS; W.E.B. DuBois Papers; U of Massachusetts, Amherst
  - DuBois to Washington (part of signature torn off), 14 November 1903, Atlanta, 1 page (Box 1)
    DuBois declines to give further advice "which will not be followed"; requests to see final list of invitees.
  - McKinlay to Washington, 16 November 1903, Washington, 1 page (Box 1)
    McKinlay met with Carruthers, who now wishes to meet with Washington.
  - Washington to McKinlay, 18 November 1903, New York City, 1 page (Box 1)
    Washington agrees to meet with Carruthers; he will meet with Hayes and Fortune; he is pleased that McKinlay has met with Dr. Grimke and hopes that the latter will attend January conference.
  - Washington to Francis J. Grimke, 19 November 1903, New York City, 3 pages (Box 1)
    Washington invites Grimke to attend New York conference to be held January 6-8, 1904.
  - Washington to Clement G. Morgan, 19 November 1903, New York City, 3 pages (Box 1)
    Neither place nor date indicated on this letter, but its text is exactly the same as that sent to Grimke on 19 November 1903 from New York.
  - Washington to Grimke, 22 November 1903, New York City, 2 pages (Box 1)
    As per Grimke's request, Washington encloses list of conference attendees; he briefly explains how he chose invitees.
  - Washington to Fortune, 22 November 1903, New York City, 1 page (incomplete?) (Box 1)
    Washington justifies decision to invite Lyons and not Pledger to attend conference; also explains reasons for not inviting A.D. Griffin and Gov. Pinchback.
  - Grimke to Washington, 25 November 1903, Washington, DC, 2 pages (Box 1)
    In response to Washington's request, Grimke suggests a few names to invite to conference.
  - R.R. Moton to Washington, 25 November 1903, Hampton, Virginia, 1 page (Box 1)
    Moton accepts invitation to attend January conference.
  - E.C. Morris to Washington, 25 November 1903, Helena, Arkansas, 1 page (Box 1)
    Morris not sure he can attend January conference, though expresses desire to aid in any way.
  - Washington to Grimke, 26 November 1903, Boston, 1 page (Box 1)
    Washington wishes to confirm receipt of list of conference attendees.
  - Washington to Morris, 1 December 1903, location unknown, 1 page (Box 1)
    Washington stresses importance of Morris's presence at January conference.
  - Morris to Washington, 8 December 1903, Helena, Arkansas, 1 page (Box 1)
    Morris will try to rearrange schedule so that he may attend conference.
  - Frederick L. McGhee to Washington, 22 December 1903, Saint Paul, Minnesota, 2 pages (Box 1)
    McGhee reluctant to attend conference due to workload, but will travel to NYC if Washington feels his presence to be necessary.
  - Hayes to Washington, 22 December 1903, Richmond, Virginia, 1 page (Box 1)
    Hayes had hoped to see Washington during his recent trip to NYC; he will attend conference in January; he wishes to meet with Washington in person.
  - John S. Durham to Washington, 26 December 1903, Havana, 2 pages (Box 1)
    Author regrets that he received Washington's letter too late to write to Morris, but hopes to bring the two men together some day; author refers to his continued work in Havana, the likelihood of Roosevelt as candidate, and a recent agitation at Trinity College as reported in Raleigh's newspaper, The News and Observer.
  - Barry to Washington, 2 January 1904, New York City, 1 page (Box 1)
    Letter in reference to Washington's booking of rooms for conference.
  - Washington to DuBois, 2 January 1904, Tuskegee, Alabama, 2 pages (Box 1)
    Washington, against his own inclination, has followed DuBois's advice and invited Archibald Grimke to conference.
  - Miller to Washington, 20 January 1904, Washington, DC, 1 page (Box 1)
    Miller will request that Browne make a copy of proceedings and forward it to Washington; Miller concerned that conferees have broken pledge of secrecy.
  - Washington to Fortune, 23 January 1904, location unknown, 1 page (Box 1)
    Washington asks Fortune to write to Judge and Mrs. Terrell explaining why there were not included in New York conference.
  - DuBois to Browne, 26 January (1904?), Atlantic City, 1 page (Box 1)
    Due to illness, DuBois cannot attend St. Louis conference.
  - Washington to Manning, 2 February 1904, location unknown, 1 page (Box 1)
    Washington wishes to meet with Manning in person in reference to the latter's recent editorial concerning the New York conference.
  - Washington to Scott, 8 July 1904, South Weymouth, Massachusetts, 1 page (Box 1)
    Washington reports a satisfactory meeting of the Committee of Twelve, despite DuBois's absence.
  - DuBois to Hugh Browne, 13 July 1904, Des Moines, 1 page (Box 1)
    DuBois informs Brown that he did not know of July 6th meeting.
  - Washington to Browne, 15 July 1904, South Weymouth, Massachusetts, 2 pages (Box 1)
    Washington confirms knowledge of Grimke's resignation and requests suggestions for his replacement.
  - Washington to Browne, 21 July 1904, South Weymouth, Massachusetts, 1 page (Box 1)
    Washington requests that Browne inform DuBois about previous notices sent to him and the group's disappointment in him.
  - DuBois to Browne, 1 August 1904, Des Moines, 1 page (Box 1)
    DuBois resigns from Committee of Twelve.
  - Washington to Browne, 14 August 1904, South Weymouth, Massachusetts, 1 page (Box 1)
    Washington asks Browne to inform DuBois that no one can accept his resignation; the latter remains a member of the committee until its next meeting; Washington also requests Browne's opinion as to when to hold their next meeting.
  - Browne to Washington, 18 August 1904, Cheyney, Pennsylvania, 1 page (Box 1)
    Browne requests that the Committee of Twelve meet in September to appoint the executive committee; he has notified DuBois and Grimke that only the Committee can accept their resignations.
  - Miller to Washington, 22 September 1904, Washington, DC, 1 page (Box 1)
    Miller suggests that Ogden gather support of Southern men; he regrets DuBois's resignation; he congratulates Washington's securing of $200,000 for his institution.
  - Washington to Browne, 18 October 1904, Tuskegee, 1 page (Box 1)
    Washington supports Browne's idea to have their work reported in newspapers, but suspects nothing will be written until after upcoming election.
  - Browne to Washington, 17 November 1904, Cheyney, Pennsylvania, 1 page (Box 1)
    Browne reports on those supporting publication of Grimke's article.
  - DuBois to Browne, 17 November 1904, Atlanta, 1 pages (Box 1)
    DuBois refuses all connections with the Committee of Twelve.
  - Washington to Browne, 28 December 1904, Tuskegee, 1 page (Box 1)
    Washington praises Browne's work on circulars; reports that he and Miller have met with Ogden and "other white people" in NYC.
  - Miller to Washington, 4 January 1905, Washington, DC, 1 page (Box 1)
    Miller will heed Washington's advice to postpone meeting with religious leaders, though he is in favor of still holding said meeting.
  - Browne to Washington, 7 February 1905, Cheyney, Pennsylvania, 2 pages (Box 1)
    Browne requests Washington's presence at dedicatory reception at the Institute for Colored Youth; he suggests that the Committee of Twelve meet again in March; he comments upon Washington's kind suggestion and willingness to promote the Institute's summer school for teachers.
  - Browne to Washington, 17 February 1905, Cheyney, Pennsylvania, 1 page (Box 1)
    Browne suggests that the Committee of Twelve meet again March 9th in New York.
  - Browne to Washington, 22 February 1905, Cheyney, Pennsylvania, 1 page (Box 1)
    Browne requests Washington's opinion on enclosure (not included); also requests place and time of day for meeting to be held March 9th.
  - Washington to Miller, 7 March 1905, New York City, 1 page (Box 1)
    Washington requests Miller's presence at meeting March 10th.
  - Washington to Miller, 8 March 1905, New York City, 1 page (Box 1)
    Washington requests Miller to arrive on earliest train.
  - Miller to Washington, telegram, 8 March 1905, Washington, 1 page (Box 1)
    Miller responds that he cannot come until Friday night or Saturday morning.
  - Morris to Washington, 21 March 1905, Helena, Arkansas, 1 page (Box 1)
    Morris cannot attend planned conference in July, and suggests they change date to August; requests that Washington speak to the President concerning the difficulties of young black men entering politics.
  - Washington to Miller, 31 March 1905, New York City, 1 page (Box 1)
    Washington suggests plan to make their work known to a broader audience.
  - Washington to Miller, 17 May 1905, location unknown, 1 page (Box 1)
    (Signature extremely faded due to water stain.) Washington suggests they postpone Hampton conference.
  - Browne to Committee, 24 May 1905, Cheyney, Pennsylvania, 3 pages (Box 1)
    Browne lists resolutions passed at last meeting of the Committee of Twelve as well as updates on their progress.
  - Browne to Washington, 25 May 1905, Cheyney, Pennsylvania, 1 page (Box 1)
    Browne wishes Washington to read and approve aforementioned form letter.
  - Miller to Washington, 3 June 1905, Washington, DC, 1 page (Box 1)
    Miller agrees to postponement of meeting; inquires as to acceptance of Chesnutt and McGee to join Committee.
  - Browne to Washington, 8 August 1905, Cheyney, Pennsylvania, 1 page (Box 1)
    Browne would like to set meeting to see Washington; he has forwarded him twenty copies of the pamphlet What a Colored Man Should Do to Vote.
  - Alexander Walters to Washington, 6 September 1905, Jersey City, New Jersey, 2 pages (Box 1)
    Walters reports surprising success of Council and those who attended.
  - Browne to Washington, 23 September 1905, Cheyney, Pennsylvania, 1 page (incomplete) (Box 1)
    Browne reports on several business matters: he encloses proceedings from previous meeting of the Committee of Twelve (see below); Grimke's letter is ready; names have been collected as suggested by Chestnutt; he will call meeting for religious group; he will meet with Maryland people concerning disfranchisement.
  - I. Garland Penn to Washington, 4 October 1905, Atlanta, 2 pages (Box 1)
    Penn writes concerning the last meeting and future meeting of the Negro Young Peoples' Christian and Educational Congress; he requests Washington's support of their program.
  - Washington to Miller, 7 October 1905, location unknown, 1 page (Box 1)
    Washington prefers to postpone their meeting with religious leaders until Miller returns from West Indies.
  - Penn to Washington, 25 November 1905, Atlanta, 1 page (Box 1)
    Penn wishes to hold meeting of the Executive committee on January 3rd as planned.
  - Penn to Washington, 9 December 1905, Atlanta, 1 page (Box 1)
    Penn announces change of date for meeting of Executive Committee.
  - Miller to Washington, 15 December 1905, Washington, DC, 2 pages (Box 1)
    Miller proposes topics to discuss with religious leaders as well as names of certain religious leaders.
  - Penn to Washington, 26 December 1905, South Atlanta, 1 page (Box 1)
    Penn has arranged meeting of the executive committee.
  - Penn to Washington, 29 December 1905, South Atlanta, 1 page (Box 1)
    Penn agrees to allow a member of the Committee of Twelve to report on their work at his upcoming meeting in Washington, DC.
  - Morris to Washington, 5 January 1906, Helena, Arkansas, 2 pages (Box 1)
    Morris can meet with Committee of Twelve in February; suggests holding meeting of religious leaders in August; Morris reminds Washington of his pledge to assist as liaison between National Baptist Convention and the President.
  - Grimke to Washington, 5 January 1906, Washington, DC, 1 page (Box 1)
    Grimke accepts proposal to postpone meeting of the Committee of Twelve.
  - Browne to Washington, 18 January 1906, Cheyney, Pennsylvania, 2 pages (Box 1)
    Browne suggests they postpone meeting between the Executive Committee of the Negro Young People's Christian and Educational Congress and the Committee of Twelve.
  - Browne to Washington, 18 January 1906, Cheyney, Pennsylvania, 1 page (Box 1)
    Browne writes to inform Washington of Frederick McGhee's refusal to join Committee of Twelve; he has enclosed McGhee's letter to that effect (not included).
  - Miller to Washington, 19 January 1906, Washington, DC, 2 pages (Box 1)
    Miller proposes they send a man to Washington to advise them of congressional activities.
  - Miller to Washington, 28 January 1906, Washington, DC, 2 pages (Box 1)
    Miller cannot remain in New York to meet with Committee of Twelve; Miller and McKinlay have just met with Sen. Dolliver concerning railroad travel measures.
  - Miller to Washington, 31 January 1906, Washington, DC, 1 page (Box 1)
    Miller can now remain in town for Committee of Twelve meeting.
  - Miller to Washington, 6 February 1906, Washington, DC, 2 pages (part of page 2 missing) (Box 1)
    Miller and Grimke have engaged H.W. Blair to "watch every move" concerning the railroads rate bill in Congress; Miller requests a check for $150 to pay him.